Good morning everybody. Sorry for the late start. Today’s דף daf is
ל"א, Lamed Aleph, 31. We pick up at the very last line
of ל' עמוד ב'. Lamed Amud Bet. So again,
today's is ל"א Lamed Aleph and we’re at the last line of
ל' עמוד ב', Lamed Amud Bet, or the second to last line.
Okay, אמר רב אסי. Amar Rav Assi. So we’re still dealing with
issues about סתם יינם stam yeinam and yesterday there was a whole
discussion, we really sort of digressed and talked a lot about גילוי,
giluy, things that are exposed and problems of snakes, but the important
upshot about סתם יינם stam yeinam was that if it’s sort of,
if it’s been turned into vinegar or if it’s been cooked, then
it cannot become סתם יינם. stam yeinam. If it already was handled
or whatever, produced by non-Jews, those changes won’t, won’t make a difference,
like, like cooking חזיר, chazir, it’s not going to make it kosher.
But if it was for cooked first, then it is not and
that’s our whole reality of יין מבושל. Yayin Mevushal. So now anyway,
the גמרא Gemara goes, the גמרא Gemara now has a nice little
categorization of different types of wines and their different halakhic status. אמר
רב אסי אמר ר' יוחנן Amar Rav Assi Amar Rabbi Yochanan said
רב אסי Rav Assi in the name of ר' יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
משום ר' יהודה בן בתירא, mishum Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira, שלושה יינות
הן. shloshah yeinos hein. There are three types of wine: red, white
and rosé.
יין נסך אסור בהנאה. Yayin Nesech assur behana'ah. Wine that was actually
poured to עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, one is forbidden to derive benefit
from.
ומטמא טומאה חמורה כזית. umetamei tumah chamurah kichazayis. And the הלכה halakha
is that we treat stuff that actually was offered to עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah as if it is the טומאה, tumah, like the association
of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah with things that are טמא. tamei. And
this is a משנה mishnah in שבת Shabbat or whatever, we treat
it as if it is a dead body, a corpse, as the
פסוק pasuk says זבחי מתים. zivchei meisim. So even, so right, זבחי
מתים, zivchei meisim, exactly. So even one כזית kezayis of it causes
טומאה tumah and a very heavy טומאה tumah and even טומאה tumah
if you don’t touch it, even if you just carry it and
so on, it’s like, it’s a corpse. Okay, top of ל"א. Lamed
Aleph. סתם יינם, stam yeinam, their, you
know, non-specific wine. Okay, I think this is the first use of
the word סתם יינם stam yeinam in the גמרא, Gemara, right? Before
it said יין של עובדי כוכבים yayin shel ovdei kochavim or whatever.
Here it’s contrasted to יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, wine that you know
was poured. Here it is, they’re סתם יינם, stam yeinam, their unspecific
wine, general wine that comes from them. Okay, אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah,
it is forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, that is because since it’s not
just about intermarriage, it’s about עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah concerns, you know,
that’s at least the context in which we framed it. So we
do make it forbidden to derive benefit. As I told you, one
interesting הלכה halakha that shows the two categories of סתם יינם stam
yeinam is wine that comes from a גר תושב Ger Toshav or
רמב"ם Rambam like Muslims or whatever, those that are not concerned for
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it is, you can’t drink it because of
intermarriage issues, but you are allowed to derive benefit. But סתם יינם
stam yeinam the standard category here is, is that because it’s based
on עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah concerns even though it was not, we
don’t know it was poured to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. אסור בהנאה,
assur behana'ah, you cannot derive benefit. ומטמא טומאת משקין ברביעית. umetamei tumas
mashkin birevi'is. And you treat it as if it became a light
level of impurity, as if it became impure by touching some, let’s
say, you know, a dead corpse or a dead rodent or whatever
the case might be. So as if it is a ראשון לטומאה,
rishon letumah, so it can make foods טמא tamei but it can’t
make people טמא. tamei. So that’s one degree removed and only if
there is a רביעית. revi'is. A רביעית revi'is is like the amount
you make קידוש kiddush on, three and a half ounces. Anything less
than that does not have that impurity. That’s a low level of
impurity. It’s interesting here the intersection, right,
of forbidden foods and impurity. You know, the תורה Torah says, I
mean this isn’t, I’m not saying this is where the גמרא’s Gemara
necessarily coming from, when the תורה Torah describes the non-kosher foods, particularly
the non-kosher species of animals, אל תטמאו בכל אלה אלה הטמאים לכם
בכל הארץ. al titame'u bechol eileh eileh hateme'im lachem bechol ha'aretz. Right,
it uses the word טומאה tumah to refer to things that cannot
be eaten. So here actually you have actual laws of טומאה וטהרה
tumah ve'taharah together with, okay, and this but presumably it’s linked in
a world of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
in particular is a sense of taboo, totally hands off, like we
saw. Real stuff that was offered to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is
even treated like a dead body. Okay, now that’s number two. And
number three is המפקיד יינו אצל עובד כוכבים. hamifkid yeino eitzel oved
kochavim. Let’s say you have wine that you produced, so far untouched
by a non-Jew. Now you have a non-Jew to watch it for
you.
This is unsealed.
Oh, well we’ll get to unsealed in a minute. אסור בשתייה ומותר
בהנאה. assur bishtiyah umutar behana'ah. So that is a middle level, that
you can’t drink it but you can derive benefit. Of course the
question is like, make up your mind. If you’re afraid he touched
it, then it should be אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. If you’re, if
you’re not afraid, it should be מותר בשתייה. mutar bishtiyah. By the
way, I should also say that we are taking for granted, which
is the הלכה, halakha, the גמרא’s Gemara taking for granted, that as
soon as a non-Jew touches it, he makes it סתם יינם, stam
yeinam, right? That wasn’t said, right? The משנה mishnah said their wine.
In the משנה mishnah you could have maybe imagined only wine that
they produced, right? Not wine of ours that they happened to touch
and so on. Okay, but that is the הלכה halakha and that
is what this גמרא’s Gemara assuming, that if they even if they
just touch it, it becomes סתם יינם. stam yeinam. המניח יינו בבית?
Hamaniah yeino beveit?
Yeah, I mean, but we’ll see about that, I don’t, we’ll see
about that. Okay, so a lot of that comes up at the
end of the מסכת. masechet. Okay, now,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. והתנן, ve'hatnan, now one minute,
the גמרא Gemara says how do you explain this הלכה? halakha? last
category? We taught in a משנה, Mishnah, המפקיד
פירות Hamafkid peirot פירותיו אצל עובד כוכבים, peirotav etzel oveid kochavim, if
you have a non-Jew watch your fruit for you, הרי הן כפירותיו
של עובד כוכבים, harei hein k'peirotav shel oveid kochavim, you have to
treat it just as if it was his fruit, meaning you're concerned
that he's going to swap your, you know, your higher quality for
his lesser quality, and therefore you just have to work with the
assumption that when you get it back, you're getting back his fruit.
Okay? He just has to assume that they were swapped. So what
would be the story if you got back his fruit? So the
הלכה Halakha would be, this is now not a סתם יינם, Stam
Yeinam, excuse me, this is something in דמאי, Demai, so the הלכה
Halakha would be לשביעית ולמעשר, l'Shevi'it ul'Ma'aser, that you have to, you
know, treat it for שמיטה Shmita purposes and for מעשר Ma'aser purposes
as if it was his. That's actually interesting, often שמיטה Shmita purposes
more lenient, right? But okay, I don't want to get into the
שמיטה Shmita part.
Maybe he's doing some הערמה, ha'aramah, you give it to your non-Jew...
No, that's not the point, Michael. Okay, it's שמיטה לחומרא, Shmita l'chumra,
not לקולא. l'kula. Okay, I don't want to discuss the specifics. But
for מעשר, Ma'aser, you know, מעשר Ma'aser also you could say if
יש קנין לעובד כוכבים, yeish kinyan l'oveid kochavim, but no, it means
the opposite. It means you have to assume the worst about the
fruit. You'd have to take תרומה Terumah and מעשר? Ma'aser? You can't
eat it unless... Correct. Correct. You have to assume the worst. Okay,
now, so anyway the basic point is, without getting into שמיטה Shmita
and מעשר, Ma'aser, that if you have him watch it, then you
have to assume that maybe he swapped it and it's the worst.
So here too, if you have him watch your wine, you have
to assume he swapped it and it's his wine. So the גמרא
Gemara says, כגון שיחד לו קרן זוית. k'gon she'yiched lo keren zavit.
You designated a corner for it. Now what good is designating a
corner going to do for it? So רש"י Rashi basically says, well
what it means is you designate a corner, for example, and you
locked it in a room and you took the key, or something
of that nature. Okay, you have some way in which you're sure
he can't tamper with it. Or he put it in... Yeah, I'm
sorry, he put it in a corner and you, he gave you
the key. Correct. You took the, you have the key. אי הכי,
Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, בשתיה נמי לישתרי? bish'tiya nami lish'trei?
So make up your mind. So then let it be permissible to
drink. What's this middle position? דאמר רב יוחנן, D'amar Rav Yochanan, איקלע
לפרהוד. ikla l'Parhod. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan came to this case פרהוד.
Parhod. אמר כלום יש משנת בר קפרא? Amar klum yeish mishnat Bar
Kappara? So the פרהוד Parhod was where בר קפרא Bar Kappara lived,
and בר קפרא Bar Kappara had died. Okay? And he wanted to
try to recover any of the teachings of בר קפרא Bar Kappara
that had possibly been lost. So he went to this place where
בר קפרא Bar Kappara had lived and he said, does anybody here
know of any teachings of בר קפרא? Bar Kappara? כלום יש משנת
בר קפרא? Klum yeish mishnat Bar Kappara? תנא ליה רב תנחום דמן
פרהוד. Tana leih Rav Tanchum d'min Parhod. So this רב תנחום Rav
Tanchum from this place, from פרהוד, Parhod, taught to him. Here's what
I heard from בר קפרא. Bar Kappara. המפקיד יינו אצל עובד כוכבים
מותר בשתייה. Hamafkid yeino etzel oveid kochavim mutar bish'tiya. If you give
it over to a non-Jew to watch, you can even drink it.
We're not afraid he tampered with it. It's not clear what the
context is, but okay, presumably we mean a context in which you're
reasonably confident he didn't tamper with it, like this case of designating
a place and you assume he wouldn't go into that place and
so on. So you see it's completely permissible. There's no middle ground.
If you're afraid he tampered with it, it should be forbidden in
benefit. If you're not afraid, it should be permissible to drink. What
is this middle ground? So before we finish though, this story about
a rediscovery, this lost teaching of בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, it says,
קרי
עליה, kari aleih, so he declared on him, so he read this
following פסוק pasuk about this person that taught this teaching of בר
קפרא. Bar Kappara. מקום שיפול העץ שם יהוא. Makom she'yipol ha'eitz sham
yehu. The place where the tree falls, there it will remain. שם
יהוא סלקא דעתך? Sham yehu salka datchach? There it will be, meaning
בר קפרא Bar Kappara was the tree, this great teacher, he died,
so he remains there. Now what does that mean? It doesn't just
mean he's buried there, he remains in a sense like he's still
there. What do you mean he's still there? He's dead. שם יהוא
סלקא דעתך? Sham yehu salka datchach? אלא שם יהו פירותיו. Ella sham
yehu peirotav. No, but his fruit is still there. His teachings are
still present in the place where he died. Which also, as רש"י
Rashi says, means if you want to go find, like it's good
that he took this visit to this place, because if you want
to recover the teachings of this teacher, you know, you have to
go back to where the teacher was and that's where you'll be
able to find, you know, his teachings and his fruit. Okay, anyway,
so bottom line though is, if you're not afraid, it should be
permissible to be eaten. So אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, לא
קשיא. lo kashya. It's not difficult. הא רבי אליעזר הא רבנן. Ha
Rabbi Eliezer ha rabanan. It's a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and the רבנן rabanan how we treat this after the, how we
treat this
in a case where you're relatively confident it wasn't tampered with. דתניא,
D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, אחד הלוקח ואחד השוכר בית
בחצירו של עובד כוכבים, echad halokei'ach v'echad hasocheir bayit b'chatzeiro shel oveid
kochavim, whether a person purchases or whether a person rents a house
in the courtyard owned by a non-Jew. So the non-Jew owns the
entire, you know,
courtyard with all the buildings, and you rent one house. ומלאו יין.
Umilo'o yayin. Now let's say you go ahead and you fill your
house with wine. I hope with barrels of wine, okay, otherwise it's
going to be, ruin the carpets. ומפתח וחותם ביד ישראל. U'maftei'ach v'chotam
b'yad Yisrael. So here it is, he has sort of like control
over, like it's in his domain, right? The house, I mean, imagine
it's even like a warehouse, right?
He can just go into your house.
I know, so that's the point. Okay, you've got the warehouse, you
know, you're leaving it, he's the one controlling the area, but you're
taking the key with you. Or you have it sealed, okay? And
presumably it would be obvious if the seal was tampered with. One
seal? One seal, correct. And presumably it would be obvious if the
seal was tampered with. So what's the הלכה? Halakha?
רבי אליעזר מתיר וחכמים אוסרין. Rabbi Eliezer matir v'chachamim osrin. So now
again, it does seem like it's one extreme or the other. We're
still looking for this middle position. But רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
it's permissible.
So now the point is if there is some type of a
seal or protection or whatever, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and בר
קפרא Bar Kappara are saying that fine, it's totally permissible and the
חכמים Chachamim are saying it's forbidden. Now you still don't have, even
הנאה hana'ah presumably you still don't have the middle position,
so we're still going to look for that. אמר רב חייא בריה
דרבי חייא בר נחמני אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chiya brei d'Rabbi
Chiya bar Nachmani amar Rav Chisda, okay אמר רב, amar Rav, so
this whole teaching in the name of רב, Rav, ואמרי לה v'amri
lah and some say אמר רב חסדא אמר זעירי amar Rav Chisda
amar Ze'iri ואמרי לה v'amri lah אמר רב חסדא אמר לי אבא
בר חמא הכי אמר זעירי, amar Rav Chisda amar li Abba bar
Chama hachi amar Ze'iri, fine, three different versions of this teaching, הלכה
כרבי אליעזר. halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer. So first of all take a deep
breath, we rule like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, very important, if we
get a chance I'll read you a line from תוספות, Tosafot, okay,
about that this was very important when they handled wine and they
shipped it from place to place, what type of seal did they
have to put on it? Did they have to be afraid that
the non-Jew?
You know wine in
the shul or whatever it is.
Right so it's עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim. What was the dominant religion?
Right so by the way עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim here is all
a censored word, the original word in all these cases is basically
נוכרי nokhri or גוי, goy, I mean does anybody here have, what
does he have there? גוי. goy. Everything's גוי. goy. Everything is גוי.
goy. Okay, the dominant religion in בבל Bavel was
Zoroastrianism. Yeah, but anyway stars?
No, the
גמרא Gemara what's here is not distinguishing between what type of non-Jew,
the word עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim, the word was גוי goy in
the גמרא. Gemara. But anyway for תוספות, Tosafot, yes, it's a big
issue, I mean for us too, but they were in the wine
business, I mean I guess Jews are also in the wine business
now, but I'm just right, so, but anyway עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim
sounds much more offensive.
I understand, but the original word is גוי. goy. Okay anyway so
that's a whole question about how do we rule? So this is
important that one חותם chotam is enough. Okay, but we still haven't
figured out this middle position.
אמר רב אלעזר, Amar Rav Elazar, so now we're רב אלעזר Rav
Elazar the אמורא, Amora, הכל משתמר בחותם אחד חוץ מן היין שאין
משתמר בחותם אחד. hakol mishtamer b'chotam echad chutz min hayayin she'ein mishtamer
b'chotam echad. So everything you is protected, remember at the beginning of
our discussion we talked about vinegar and other types of things that
one seal is enough and therefore you're not afraid it's tampered with,
but this seems like actually he is taking the Rabbi's position, the
רבנן Rabbanan against רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and you know בר קפרא.
Bar Kappara. They, you know he's afraid no, one seal for wine,
other things one seal is enough, wine maybe they're so eke, maybe
it's expensive, you know, maybe good wine some people have a real
תאווה taivah for, maybe because of they want to use it for
their עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, whatever it is there's too big of
a יצר הרע yetzer hara by wine one seal is not enough.
Depends on how good the seal is.
All right, so the גמרא's Gemara going to deal with a higher
level seal, okay, so that that is a question, right, so the
גמרא's Gemara going to deal. So why do we double cork? Wait
wait wait, you, that's completely unrelated. Okay, that so it doesn't puncture
and get treifed up. Okay anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, so that presumably is the position of the חכמים Chachamim
that argue with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer one seal is not enough.
We still again don't understand the middle position חוץ מן היין שאין
משתמר בחותם אחד ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו יין משתמר בחותם אחד. chutz
min hayayin she'ein mishtamer b'chotam echad v'Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu yayin mishtamer
b'chotam echad. No, even wine is just like everything else, one seal
is enough to ensure that it hasn't been tampered with. You know
this is of course what happened by the way when who remembers
oh my god how many years ago was it 30 years with
the whole thing with the Tylenol and the you know and they
somebody tampered with the Tylenol and they some what did they do
poisoned it or something, anyway that's why they started creating these tamper-proof
bottles so that you would see if it had been tampered with
because somebody actually you know had done something like
this. Anyway ולא פליגי, v'lo pligi, so now the גמרא Gemara says
ולא פליגי v'lo pligi they're not debating, well they are debating but
it means that they're really, you know, not debating within the same
tannaic position. חד כרבי אליעזר וחד כרבנן. Chad k'Rabbi Eliezer v'chad k'rabbanan.
One is adopting the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is lenient says if you have the wine by the
non-Jew in some type of a protected scenario it's okay, one seal
is enough. And the other say no, one seal isn't enough okay.
איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri some say אמר רב אלעזר הכל משתמר בחותם
בתוך חותם חוץ מן היין שאין משתמר בחותם בתוך חותם. amar Rav
Elazar hakol mishtamer b'chotam betoch chotam chutz min hayayin she'ein mishtamer b'chotam
betoch chotam. So this is now, I'm just going to jump ahead
the גמרא's Gemara going to say, this is now within the רבנן
Rabbanan who disagree with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and say that one
and say that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says one seal is enough,
רבנן Rabbanan don't say it's not enough. And now he's saying for
the rabbis who disagree with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and say that
one seal is not enough even two seals are not enough. Everything
else two seals is okay except wine שאין משתמר בחותם בתוך חותם
she'ein mishtamer b'chotam betoch chotam even a double seal is not enough
with wine. Nothing is basically okay? ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו יין משתמר
בחותם בתוך חותם. v'Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu yayin mishtamer b'chotam betoch chotam.
No, two seals is fine for wine. ותרווייהו כרבנן V'tarvaihu k'rabbanan and
they're both working within the rabbis, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and בר
קפרא Bar Kappara are saying even one seal is fine. The rabbis
reject that. So what would be good for the rabbis? So one
is saying, well two seals and the other saying nothing would be
good for the rabbis. Okay? So ותרווייהו כרבנן. v'tarvaihu k'rabbanan. מר סבר
כי פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר בחותם אחד Mar savar ki pligi
rabbanan alei d'Rabbi Eliezer b'chotam echad they're only disagreeing with one seal,
but two seals they would concede is okay אבל בחותם בתוך חותם
שרי. aval b'chotam betoch chotam shari. ומר סבר Umar savar and the
other position says אפילו חותם בתוך חותם אסירא afilu chotam betoch chotam
asiri that no, they would even reject two seals okay? So now
we have the basic way of framing the debate, let's go with
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to read of framing the debate of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the rabbis. What do you need to protect
wine and make sure it hasn't been tampered with? One seal or
two seals? Okay, we'll assume that for other things, presumably based on
the גמרא Gemara we learned at the beginning of this,
the beginning of the discussion, one seal is generally enough for other
things. What
do you need for wine? Is one seal enough? That's what רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, or do you need two seals? Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara is going to, now we still haven't really fully
explained the middle position. Don't worry about why it could be forbidden
to drink and מותר בהנאה. mutar be'hana'ah. We'll wind our way back
to it. But first we're going to describe what is two seals.
היכי דמי חותם בתוך חותם? Heichi dami chotam betoch chotam? What would
be an example of this?
אמר רבא אגנא דפומא
דחביתא סריכא וחתימא. Amar Rava, agna depuma dechavita serika vechatima. So you
basically have a type of a bowl, okay, on the mouth of
a barrel and it's
plastered and sealed, okay, which basically I presume means is you have
a plaster, that's one seal, because if you break the bowl off
and then replaster it, it'll be obvious that it've been tampered with,
and then
on top of the plaster you put a seal. So you also
have to now replicate the seal, some type of a stamp or
something.
That reminds me of what we have in these bottles we have
these days. You have that plastic thing you need to twist off
and sometimes on top of that, you have that tape kind of
thing.
There you go. That's probably what it's based on. Okay, now an
important question here is, which the גמרא Gemara never explains and it'll
be clear in a minute, I would like to believe, I mean,
not because I want to, because I want to be מחמיר, machmir,
but מסברא, misvara, I would think that it was talking about that
the definition of a seal, one or two, is something that there's
a relatively likely that it'll be obvious that it was tampered with
and it would be hard to tamper and replace it without it
being obvious you had done something. But we're about to see, and
that works with this case, but we're about to see some scenarios
which sounds like a seal just means that it's something you have
to get through, not necessarily that it'll be obvious that it was
tampered, it just is an extra level of effort. Okay, so let's
take a look at the next case. Keep that in mind as
we read the next case. Okay, so that is הוי חותם בתוך
חותם, havei chotam betoch chotam, that's a seal in a seal. ואי
לא לא, V'ee lo lo, and if less than that, not. דיקולא,
Dikula, now let's say you got a basket, a wicker basket, ומהדק,
u'mehadek, and it's tight on top of the top of a barrel,
okay,
and הוי חותם בתוך חותם. havei chotam betoch chotam.
That's a double seal. Now what's the double seal? It's a tight
basket. Okay, so if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
ומהדק נכנס בתוכה פי הסל לבלוע את החבית הוי חותם בתוך חותם
ולא טרח לזיופי כולי האי. u'mehadek nichnas betochah pi hasal livloa et
hachavit havei chotam betoch chotam velo tarach leziyufei kulei hai. So you
won't go to the effort. It's just an issue of effort. It's
like it could be forged, it's easy, or it's not even forged,
it just means undoing
it. Anyway, I'm not even totally getting I have to tell you
what the double one is. רש"י Rashi says here, רש"י Rashi
wait one minute, סלא פי חבית וחבית מגופא דהיינו ב' חתמות מגופת
החבית. sala pi chavit vechavit megufa dehaynu bet chotamot megufat hachavit. Ah,
so רש"י Rashi says, I see. רש"י Rashi says that the double
seal is the normal cover that a barrel would have, that's not
even something special, you normally just when you seal a barrel, you
put on its cover. So the normal cover the barrel will have
plus this tight basket that you tight, you screwed in on the
top. Okay, but that's like doesn't seem like either of those are
hard to forge. It doesn't even seem like there's anything to forge.
It just means two things you have to get through. Is everybody
hearing my point here? Okay, so then anyway, that's the way רש"י
Rashi explained it. It's like a sealed barrel with a basket like
tightly affixed to the top. Who knows, okay? לא מהדק, Lo mehadek,
if it's not tightly affixed, לא הוי חותם בתוך חותם. lo havei
chotam betoch chotam. Here's the third case, which also seems like it's
not really an issue about can it be forged or not, but
is just two things you have to get through. נאד, Nod, let's
say you have a
flask, a leather flask that has wine in it. בדיסקייא, Bediskeya, which
is in a larger bag. חתימת פיו למטה, Chatimat piv lemata,
now what you do is you have your flask and you wrap
your string around it to seal the top, right? Okay, that's one
seal. All it is is a wrapped string. You unwrap the string
and you wrap it back. And then you put the thing upside
down in another bag. You got it? So now what you have
to do is you have to go in, pull it out, turn
it right side up and undo it. As opposed to if it
was right side up, it's just you open its external bag and
the internal bag is right there waiting for you. So the double
seal is, doesn't seem like it's a big deal here at all.
The double seal is it's sealed once, it's not in a way
that can't be forged, it's just sealed. And then it's upside down.
That's a second thing you have to do. Okay. נאד בדיסקייא חתימת
פיו למטה, Nod bediskeya chatimat piv lemata,
if the sealed mouth is at the pointing to the bottom of
the bag, הוי חותם בתוך חותם. havei chotam betoch chotam. פיו למעלה,
Piv lemala, if the mouth is facing up, so then you just
open the external bag and the internal bag is right there waiting
for you, לא הוי חותם בתוך חותם. lo havei chotam betoch chotam.
It's not double. But again, for me the point is, okay. Okay,
נוד בי דיסקייא, Node bi diskayah, חתימת פיו למטה, chatimas piv lemata,
if the sealed mouth is at the pointing to the bottom of
the bag, הוי חותם בתוך חותם. havi chosam bsoch chosam. פיו למעלה,
piv lemala, if the mouth is facing up, so then you just
open the external bag and the internal bag is right there waiting
for you, לא הוי חותם בתוך חותם, lo havi chosam bsoch chosam,
it's not double. But again, for me, the point is, okay, but
double big deal. Double's just a little bit more effort, you know?
I don't, so it seems a little formalistic here. וכי כייף פומיה
לגב, vechi chayef pumei legav, now let's say after you seal it
at first, what you do is apparently what they would do is
I sort of have have a bag here, let me see if
I can find this,
someone here left this, I don't
know who gave it to me,
okay. So here, this is my flask, okay? So if I do
this, right, if I if this is this is my חתימת פיו
chatimas piv like this, and then the second seal would be I
push this inside like this and I sort of you see what
and I sort of like do it again. Okay, so I like
take the thing and I push it in after I sealed it
and then I seal around it a second time. So וכי כייף
vechi chayef okay, וכי
כייף פומיה לגב, vechi chayef pumei legav,
if you push the mouth back inside the the flask itself and
then you seal it וצייר וחתים vetziyar vechasim and you sort of
bind it and seal it הוי חותם בתוך חותם, havi chosam bsoch
chosam, it's double. Anyway what emerges for me is, I don't it's
not even clear if even one of them has to be like
tamper-proof, has to be able to be shown that you've tampered with
it. It sounds like just a double seal, just making it like
a barrier, you know, an obstacle, but it doesn't seem like it
has to be tamper-proof.
But this according to the more strict position that you need a
חותם בתוך חותם? chosam bsoch chosam?
Right, I understand. So okay, I'm I'm you know, practically I'm happy
that it's not so demanding, but just logically I'm not understanding how
it solves so much, you know? Must be unless we're really not
in reality all that afraid it's really going to happen, you know,
it is more some type of a formal type of What what
is it?
Like when you say it is going to happen?
Right, the it is that he'll want to undo it in order
to swap it out with better with you know, the good stuff
with his stuff. That's what we're afraid of. Right, the reason of
all this is we're afraid that he's going to not he's going
to want to mess us up and touch the wine and ha-ha
I got the Jews to violate. No, it's good quality wine, he's
going to want to take it out and put in bad quality
wine.
So this משתמר. mishtamer. This place of like so something theoretically.
Right, something actually happens to the wine not just טומאה tumah and
so on.
Right, right, that's what we're afraid. Yeah, yeah, it's a totally afraid
that he's going to swap it for his wine.
Until we learn more about the winepress or
somebody that knows wine. Exactly. Just a note, just
a note here that discusses this as a clay sealing in some
of these examples.
Right,
so that's what I said. The first example certainly sounded like it
was tamper-proof, it was a clay seal, but that's not the case
about a leather flask, right?
Do they have glass bottles then? Yeah, yeah.
Uh-huh, yup. נוד node is not it and
right, a נוד node I don't understand by
a what נוד node is leather, so presumably you're using like a
string or something, right? If it does it say something there about
how the leather flask is tamper-proof? David, you see something? No picture.
No, I
don't know, I didn't see. Okay.
It said just says the knot on the flask, you can see
the first and the knot on the pouch the second.
Yeah, I understand, but okay I mean look, if it would have
said that it's a knot, you know sometimes you can do a
knot that's a very distinctive knot, right? But it's not saying that.
Now, you know, so that's just that's just what surprises me. Okay,
so now we continue. תנו רבנן. tnu rabanan. בראשונה היו אומרים, barishona
hayu omrim,
originally they used to say, יין של עין כושי אסור, yayin shel
ein kushi asur, wine from this place Ein Kushi which was a
place where there were Samaritans, okay, is forbidden. מפני בירת סריקה, mipnei
biras srika, because of the neighboring village Birat Srika where there were
non-Jews and you were just afraid because of the non-Jews and the
Samaritans whatever they would come to touch their wine. Okay, ושל בירכסא
אסור מפני כפר פרשאי, veshel birkasa asur mipnei kfar parshai, ושל זגדור
אסור מפני כפר שלים. veshel zagdur asur mipnei kfar shalim. So all
these places are Samaritan villages near villages of non-Jews. And even though
the Samaritans do not make the wine forbidden, actually at a later
stage the rabbis treated the Samaritans like non-Jews, but at this stage
no. So even though the Samaritans don't make the wine forbidden, you're
afraid because of the proximity that they're not careful that the non-Jews
touch their wine and therefore the wine is forbidden. That's what they
originally said. חזרו לומר, chazru lomar, then they took it back and
said,
חביות פתוחות אסורות סתומות מותרות. chaviyos psuchos asuros stumos mutaros. The open
barrels are forbidden, there we're afraid that non-Jews touched it, the sealed
ones are permissible. We're not afraid that non-Jews touched it before it
was sealed, we're not afraid somehow non-Jews
opened it, touched it, resealed it, like that's going a little too
far. Okay, so the Gemara says מעיקרא מאי קסברי ולבסוף מאי סברי.
meikara mai kasavri ulevsof mai savri. What was your original position and
what's your later position? Why did you change? מעיקרא סברי, meikara savri,
they felt אין כותי מקפיד על מגע עובדי כוכבים. ein kusi makpid
al maga ovdei kochavim. So by the way, here's the first point
while the Gemara's been assuming it really until now, but here it's
saying explicitly even the touch of a non-Jew makes it a problem,
right? So there's two things to be concerned about. Will a non-Jew
swap the wine or and then or will they even just touch
it? So originally they felt that the Samaritan won't be careful of
the touch of a non-Jew. לא שנא פתוחות ולא שנא סתומות, lo
shena psuchos velo shena stumos, whether it's open or sealed, which is
very funny because even if they're not careful, why would a non-Jew
go to the effort of opening a barrel, touching it, and so
on? Okay, but they just felt no, we're concerned about that scenario.
Samaritans won't care even though presumably they'll know that Jews will want
to be buying the wine from them, that they're not going to
care. Okay. ובסוף סברה, Uvesof savrah, in the end they felt, לא
כי לא קפיד אפתוחות אסתומות מקפד קפיד, lo ki lo kapid a'petuchot
astumot mikpad kapid, which maybe, you know, fine, they're not careful about
the open barrels of wine. You got an open barrel of wine
and people are coming into your store and tasting it. You know,
you've got a closed barrel of wine and you forget even because
you're you're going to sell it to Jews, you don't care about
about those הלכות, halachos, but you have a closed barrel of wine,
they don't handle my wine, you know, don't open it up. What
are you talking about? There's a story about
אחשורוש.
Achashverosh. Haman tries to heads up אחשורוש. Achashverosh.
Right, he says, a fly falls in your wine, the Jews' wine
they'll drink it. You would, if you the king would touch the
wine, they'd throw it out. Exactly. Well, look, that is the issue
why, talking about, you know, I'm glad you pointed that out, because
whatever the concern here is about, you know, עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and whatever, we have to acknowledge that the effect of of this,
it's actually very appropriate, we're only two weeks away from פורים, Purim,
right, ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. We have to acknowledge that the effect
of this ruling is that if touch a non-Jew touching something makes
it completely off-limits, right, you know, you can't eat it, you can't
even get benefit from it. You know, it changes the whole way
emotionally of like relating to the non-Jews, right? They've got cooties, they're
completely impure. We mentioned before the idea of impurity, right? So they
just touch something and they טריף treif it up. So there's like
a huge impact in terms of this, in terms of like othering,
which is exactly that מדרש midrash with המן Haman and אחשורוש. Achashverosh.
You know, המן Haman says, look, you know, on the פסוק, pasuk,
ודתיהם שונות מכל עם, vedateihem shonot mikol am, right, their practices are
ודתי המלך אינם עושים, vedatei hammelech einam osim, their religious practices are
different and they don't even do the practices of the king. He
says look at how offensive it is. If a fly were to
fall in their wine, they would throw out the fly and drink
the wine, but if the king were to touch their wine, they
would throw, you know, throw out the wine. So it's actually I
appreciate you mentioning that, very, you know, very timely, but it's yeah,
there's like a huge effect by saying just touching the wine טריףs
treif it up, you know. Okay, so anyway, so it says like
this. Anyway, but okay, now we have something more reasonable. When it's
open it's not a problem, when it's when it's open it's a
problem, you know, when it's closed, they're just going to anyway not
want people to touch their closed barrels of wine, to go and
tamper with the wine. Okay. אסתומות מותרות? Astumot mutarot? Are we really
saying that it's permissible if it's sealed? Because דאמינא, da'amina, I'll ask
you on this: השולח חבית
של יין ביד כותי. Hasholeach chavit shel yayin beyad Kuti.
So here we get exactly to this, you know, sending stuff. You
know, you have to get your wine transported, can you have a
non-Jew transport it, can you have a Samaritan transport it? So here
you are, you're sending it by a Samaritan. ושל, Veshel, okay, and
the point is going to be in all these cases the stuff
has to have a seal on it. Okay. So the assumption here
just before we read further because it'll get a little confusing is
that if you're sending wine by a Samaritan, you have to have
a seal. So you see, and you're afraid otherwise you're afraid that
either he'll tamper with it or he'll let a non-Jew tamper with
it. So you see, says the גמרא, Gemara, the point of this
is that just that it's sort of normally closed is not enough.
You need a special seal in order to protect it from being
tampered, even if it's in the hands of a Samaritan. Okay. השולח
חבית של יין ביד כותי. Hasholeach chavit shel yayin beyad Kuti.
Good Samaritan, exactly. If he's a good Samaritan, he won't tamper with
it, thank you. השולח חבית של יין ביד כותי ושל ציר ושל
מורייס, Hasholeach chavit shel yayin beyad Kuti veshel tzir veshel muryes, or
if it's fish brine or מורייס muryes which is also like a
type of a fish hash with wine mixed into it, ביד עובדי
כוכבים, beyad ovdei kochavim, in the hands of a non-Jew, okay, and
the con so אם מכיר חותמו וסתימתו מותר. im makir chotamo usetimato
mutar.
So here actually it is talking about that yes, it's not just
enough that it was an obstacle. Here it's clarifying that a חותם
chotam as opposed to what the עמוד א׳ Amud Aleph sounded like
is at least something that you it will be recognizable to you,
you know, at the end. So if it was undone and redone,
you will see somehow, hey, wait, that's not the way I did
it. Okay. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, and if it does not look
recognizable, אסור, assur, it's forbidden. So the point for us is, now
just so you know, what's the issue with the fish hash? The
issue with the fish hash and so on is that or the
fish brine is a similar thing, the non-Jew will say, oh, this
is high quality fish brine, let me swap it for my low
quality fish brine, and the low quality fish brine is from a
non-kosher fish. By the way, a slight little digression, when
there is a high degree of fraud in in fish that is
in the labeling of fish. You go to the supermarket even if
you go to a restaurant, okay, so because, you know, high quality
fish the difference in price between high quality fish and low quality
fish can be huge. So they will often, you know, use low
quality fish and label it as high quality fish. So that's really
becomes כשרות kashrut issues too, if it's not really recognizable like something
like tuna or whatever, can you really trust it if you don't
see the stuff on? You know, sometimes the גמרא Gemara was concerned
about fraud, the גמרא Gemara wasn't making it up. Okay. So anyway,
the issue about brine is you're concerned that they'll switch it with
lower quality with lower quality that is טרף. treif. The concern about
the fish hash is a little different. According to רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*,
it's that the fish hash includes a mixture of wine. And apparently,
wine itself is cheaper per ounce or whatever than the fish hash.
So what you're afraid they'll do is they'll take out some of
the hash and water it down or with wine, you know, and
then they'll put their wine in it. So those last two cases
are cases you're afraid that they'll swap it. So therefore, but if
they, if the non-Jew touched it, it wouldn't be a problem. So
in those cases, it's only a problem if a non-Jew is transporting
it. You got it? Because you're afraid he'll swap it. If a
Samaritan is transporting it, you then since touch won't matter, and you're
not afraid that the, you know, and you're not afraid for swapping,
that's only if it's a non-case of a non-Jew, okay, then that's
okay. So that's why the second case only if a non-Jew's transporting
it, but the first case, a Samaritan is transporting it, even if
he just lets a non-Jew touch it, it's an issue. So therefore,
it needs a seal. So how do you make sense? Before you
said that if their barrels were closed, it's not a problem. Here
you're saying, because they're not going to let non-Jews touch it, here
you're saying that it needs not only be closed, but it needs
to be sealed. So what's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, אמר Amar, רבי זירא *Amar Rabbi Zeira*, says רבי זירא *Rabbi
Zeira*, לא קשיא *lo kashya*, it's not difficult. כאן בעיר כאן בדרך
*kan be'ir kan baderech*. It depends whether you're in the city or
you're on the road. רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot: *Tosafos* debate what
the difference is. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* is easier explanation, I think תוספות
*Tosafos* just says if you're in the city, he's afraid other people
will see him. If he's on the road, nobody's watching. Okay, so
therefore, which presumably means that the care that the Samaritan has is
the care that he wants to be able to sell it to
Jews. Okay, so in the city, you know, he's going to be
afraid somebody will see him touch it and then I won't be
able to sell it, you know, out on the field, nobody's going
to see him. Okay, so מתקיף ליה רבי ירמיה *maskif lei Rabbi
Yirmiya*, רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiya* challenges, מידי הנך דעיר לאו בדרך אתו
*midi hanech de'ir lav bederech atu*? Yeah, great question. Those that are
now in the village, okay, how do they get to the village?
Unless they were produced locally, they were transported through the through the
way. So if he, if a Samaritan got a barrel of of
wine delivered to him and it's now in the village, how can
you say it's okay because it's sealed? It got to him by
being transported on the road, okay. So so how is
סתום *satum* enough? Don't you need it to have a חותם *chotam*?
How is closed enough? Don't you need it to have a recognizable
seal if it since it was transported to to get to him?
So again, what's the story? Why does we first sound like closed
is enough, סתום *satum*, and now we're saying you need a חותם
*chotam*? So אלא אמר רבי ירמיה *ela amar Rabbi Yirmiya*, ביני גיטי
שנינו *beina gito shaninu*, the case of where סתום *satum* is enough
is between the period of like the pressings of the wine when
people are not busy making the wine and there's a lot of
people going to the market and the town is very busy. Okay,
and כיון דכולי עלמא אהדרי *keivan dechulei alma ahadri*, since everybody is
like, you know, traveling back and forth and turning around, so מרתת
*mirtat*. In that, because of the high degree of volume, he the
the Samaritan is going to be careful and make sure that I
can't let anybody touch this wine, then the Jew won't want to
buy it. But if it is a case when it's like only
you know, person comes up to the comes to the store, like
stores are often empty, one person at a time in the store,
he's not going to be so careful to make sure that a
non-Jew doesn't touch it. Okay.
Is this geographical or seasonal? Seasonal.
Seasonal. Yeah, yeah.
How do we know this?
I mean, that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses that else other times
too, means between the like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses I I'd
have to look at the other case in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
As a time. Yeah, yeah.
Are we talking about touching the outside of the container?
No, the wine itself. Finger, your finger in it and touching the
wine itself, which raises a question like who would touch the wine
itself? But I guess if you're going to like take a taste
or something, you might do like this and you know inadvertently touch
it or something.
Why is that an issue today when about pouring?
Excellent question. So here's just a one-second digression about this. When you
pour wine, why is the wine in the cup a problem? So
this is actually all of this is debated. Some would might argue
it would not be. But the argument is that since you're causing
the wine to move by pouring it down or whatever, you know,
you're it's as if you sort of touched that wine because you
know, you you exposed it and so on. And not just you
exposed it. You sort of like made it move, it's somehow like
you touched it. But some will say maybe, first of all even
that's debated, you know, but but then the question is is about
that's like a case of כוחו *kocho*, your energy. Is your energy
making it move like you touched it? But some will say but
that doesn't apply to the wine left in the in the bottle.
Because the wine left in the bottle, you know, even I guess
he made it move within the bottle or something, but it never
you can't get your finger into it, that that the neck is
narrow, okay, it's not so it's not possible to be touched and
whatever and it was only second-degree removed from the wine that actually
got poured. So you know, ask your rabbi, I'm not going to
פסקן pasken *pasken* right now, but you know and we tend to
sort of not follow go by קולות *kullos* by סתם יינם *stam
yeinam* issues, but you know. As far as a matter of strictly,
speaking strictly from a הלכה halakhah perspective, there's good reason to say
that one could be, you know, lenient in some cases on the
wine left in the bottle, especially when you add in what I
should sort of add to this is the point that, you know,
the point that I didn't, I'm sorry I needed to have started
with that with, is the point that, you know, if we say
that Christians nowadays are not עובדי עבודה זרה. ovdei avodah zarah. So
the רמ"א Rama says that if Christians nowadays are not עובדי עבודה
זרה, ovdei avodah zarah, then we could be lenient if it's not
direct touch, if it's indirect touch. So then, you know, the wine
left in the bottle is like two degrees indirect, you know, it's
not just you didn't move it, but so anyway, there's what to
talk about if you have a בדיעבד bedi'avad case, alright? But anyway,
but you're right, to some, so
we go beyond just saying touch and we even talk about making
it move and so on, you know, that's like the next degree
removed, you're absolutely correct.
A Muslim wouldn't be any problem, right? What? A Muslim.
A Muslim would not be a problem in terms of, right, for
a Muslim in terms of the issue of בנותיהם, benotehem, that's another
important point, right? The בנותיהם, benotehem, the issue of touch is only
a problem in the עבודה זרה avodah zarah context. In the, in
the intermarriage context it's a problem that they own the wine, not
that they touched the wine. Okay, so that's another important whole issue.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: okay, talking about the issue about intermarriage, אתמר, itmar, it was
said: מפני מה אסרו שכר של עובדי כוכבים? mipnei mah asru sheikhar
shel ovdei kokhavim? Why did they say the beer of non-Jews is
forbidden? So the question you should be saying is, what do you
mean why did they say? Whoever said that? So look at תוספות:
מפני מה אסרו שכר, mipnei mah asru sheikhar, like six lines down
the wide lines, איסור שכר לא מצינו לא במשנה ולא בברייתא. issur
sheikhar lo matzinu lo bamishnah velo babraita. There's no Tannaic source. ושמא
בימי אמוראי אסרוהו. veshema bimei amora'ei asruhu. Somehow maybe somewhere in the
Amoraic period they decided it was forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara starts
by saying, why did they say it was forbidden, right? with rather
than, but like whoever said it was forbidden. Okay, and this by
the way I just will tell you at the outset, this הלכה
halakhah that we're about to learn is a הלכה halakhah, that as
they say was observed in the breach, which means basically like the
way I sometimes say it is, before the ink was even dry
in this הלכה, halakhah, people started finding ways why it wasn't relevant,
like why to say it didn't apply. Okay, because according to this
הלכה, you can't go into a bar
and drink, you know, in a non-Jewish bar, whatever. So okay, מפני
מה, mipnei mah, so we're already even in the גמרא Gemara they're
going to try to limit it. But the first part is that
the איסור issur comes out of thin air. Okay, so מפני מה
אמרו, mipnei mah amru, why did they say, אסרו שכר של עובדי
כוכבים? asru sheikhar shel ovdei kokhavim? רמי
בר חמא אמר רבי יצחק: Rami bar Chama amar Rabbi Yitzchak: משום
חתנות, mishum chasnut, intermarriage concerns,
which makes a lot of sense, I mean, you know, going out
and drinking with your pals, it's not just drinking wine. רב נחמן
אמר: Rav Nachman amar: משום גילוי. mishum gilluy. We're back to that,
because they leave it exposed and it's the poison issue.
I have another piece of trivia. Yes. The English word cider comes
from the Hebrew שכר. sheikhar.
Oh, interesting. שכר sheikhar and cider. Okay. Good trivia. So the גמרא
Gemara says: אגילוי דמאי? agilluy demai? What do we afraid was exposed?
אילימא גילוי דנזייתא, ileima gilluy denazaita, exposed when it was in like
the large cask, אנן נמי מגלינא, anan nami megallina, we also let
our שכר sheikhar be exposed, we don't think that snakes drink from
it. אלא דחביתא, ela dechavita, when it's in the barrel, the smaller
container, אנן נמי מגלינא, anan nami megallina, we also still, who cares
what container it's in, snakes don't drink from שכר. sheikhar. לא צריכא
באתרא דמצפו מייא, lo tzericha ba'atra dematzfu maya, where they water it
down or whatever, you know, where they pour water into it. So
where somehow afraid that the snakes drink from the water that was
then added to the שכר. sheikhar. So the גמרא Gemara says:
אלא מעתה, ela me'atah,
ישן תשתרי? yashan tishteri? Let old שכר sheikhar be okay? דאמר רבי:
de'amar Rabbi:
מישן מותר. miyashan muttar. אין מניחו לישן. ain manicho leyashen. That old,
if you have something that was left exposed and then you leave
it for a long period of time, then you can drink it.
Why? Because if it actually did have poison in it, then it
would, the poison after a period of time would rise to the
top and you would see it. So if you leave it for
a long period of time after it was exposed and nothing happens,
you know it's okay.
החמיץ, hikhmitz, similarly if you left something let's say wine exposed and
it became vinegar, מותר. muttar. אין מניחו להחמיץ. ain manicho lehakhmitz. The
poison in it won't allow it to become vinegar. So if it
turned into vinegar, you know that it was not poisoned. Anyway, so
if it's really a concern about exposed, why is old beer or
mead or whatever not a problem? So the גמרא says: גזירה ישן
אטו חדש. gezeirah yashan atu chadash. We're afraid the old stuff will
lead to the new stuff. Now if it's really, we normally don't
say that. We normally say if it's just a concern about being
exposed, old is okay. But clearly anyway, we're seeing that maybe it's
not really just about a concern about being exposed. You know, fine,
whatever, we extended it to even old old beer. רב פפא Rav
Pappa now. So
so that's the idea, that there's this prohibition of שכר. sheikhar. Now
we're going to get to some exceptions. רב פפא. Rav Pappa.
Did they actually was שכר sheikhar beer?
What? How was it made? Yeah, I think it was made out
of barley.
I think it's mead or beer.
I think it was beer, but I don't know, you're right I
keep on saying mead or how do they translate it, beer or
mead?
Beer. Beer. But I don't know. how שכר *sheichar* was made. Okay?
Mead is made from honey, right? Yeah. Yeah, I think this is
beer. Yeah, this is beer. Okay, so anyway, the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this: רב Rav פפא מפקין ליה אבבא דחנותא ושתא *Rav Papa
mafkin leh ababa de-chanuta ve-shatei*. רב פפא *Rav Papa* would go into
the store, buy the beer, and then step outside the store and
drink it. He just wouldn't drink it in the store itself. Okay?
רב אחא מייתו ליה לביתיה ושתא *Rav Acha meitu leh leveiteih ve-shatei*.
רב אחא *Rav Acha* would buy the beer in the store, take
it home, and drink it at home. דתרווייהו משום חתנות *detarveihu mishum
chatnut*. Now they both felt that it was an intermarriage concern. And
here's a big point, a very important point, right? Because if it's
a concern, how much in general sometimes things are motivated by intermarriage
concerns, but we say that the thing itself is טרפה *treif*. Okay,
like for example, there's a whole debate if something is cooked by
a non-Jew and one of the reasons that something cooked by a
non-Jew is not okay is because of concern that, you know, you
start eating their food, it'll lead to intermarriage. All right, so let's
say a non-Jew cooks something in my pot. Do my pots become
טרפה *treif*? So some פוסקים *poskim* will say no. If it's a
concern about intermarriage, it's not really that the food is טרפה *treif*,
it's more about don't eat it, you know, so we don't treat
the food as if it's טרפה *treif*. You know, don't eat the
food because of intermarriage, but we don't treat it as טרפה *treif*.
Others say and actually the general הלכה *halacha* is, at least לכתחילה
*lechatchila*, that we say no, it does טרפה *treif* up your pot.
Okay, wine, clearly we treat as טרפה *treif*. I mean, there's going
to be whole סוגיות *sugyot* about vessels that stored wine and whatever.
You know, it's not just about the whatever was the background reason
why we said don't drink the wine. At the end of the
day, it's not just about the act of drinking. It's about טרפה
*treif*—the wine is טרפה *treif*. So here, what it's clear is, is
that if you thought that the concern of the beer was about
intermarriage,
we didn't say the beer was טרפה *treif*. If I can step
out of the store and drink it, or take it home and
drink it, then the beer itself is not טרפה *treif* as non-kosher
food. What it means is in certain contexts, don't be drinking with
beer that, you know, you're getting from your non-Jew because that creates
too much conviviality? That's the
word. Okay, that, you know, so it's not the beer is טרפה
*treif*. Take it home! Fine! It's just don't drink it there where
you got it. That's too much of a חתנות *chatnut* issue. So
it's all very much about the context and the setting and not
about the actual beer itself. Okay? So that's what they say. דתרווייהו
משום חתנות *detarveihu mishum chatnut*. They both think it's because of חתנות
*chatnut* and therefore it's only in the immediate setting. ורב אחא עביד
הרחקה יתירתא *ve-Rav Acha avid harchaka yetirta*. And רב אחא *Rav Acha*
technically would have been enough to step outside the store, but he
was being extra מחמיר *machmir* and wanted to wait till he got
home. Of course, according to this, it would sound like if I
actually go to a bar run by a non-Jew, order a beer
and drink with my non-Jewish friends, like the scene in Fiddler, you
know, whatever, I don't know if they were friends, but like what
Jews had been doing for hundreds of years, would be אסור *assur*.
Okay, so as I said right away, there are a million explanations
about why basically no—pretty much nobody ever observes this. All right, anyway,
now the גמרא *Gemara* continues.
Back to wine. רב
שמואל בר ביסנא איקלע למרגוון *Rav Shmuel bar Bisna ikla le-Marguvan*. He
came to this place, Marguvan. אייתו ליה חמרא ולא אישתי *Aitu leh
chamra velo ishtei*. They brought him wine and he didn't drink it.
אייתו ליה שיכרא ולא אישתי *Aitu leh sheichra velo ishtei*. They brought
him beer and he didn't drink it. בשלמא חמרא משום שמצא *Bishlama
chamra mishum shimtsa*. We get that he didn't drink the wine because
the שמצא *shimtsa* is like, you know, something repulsive, which means that
it's forbidden for the reasons we've been saying. But it's an interesting
use of the word, you know, שמצא *shimtsa*. What does שמצא *shimtsa*
mean in modern Hebrew? A tiny bit?
An atom? Really? Okay, but it's often used...
right,
but usually it's like a tiny bit of something bad, right? No?
Really?
Interesting.
לשמצא בקמיהם *Le-shimtsa bekumeihem* is defamation.
Defamation. Yeah, so I think it has both of those senses, like
a trace of something bad. So the wine we get. שיכרא משום
מאי *Shichra mishum mai*? Why not the beer? משום שמצא דשמצא *Mishum
shimtsa de-shimtsa*. A trace of a trace of something bad, which basically
makes it sound like it's an extension of the wine and the
wine has to do with... also בנותיהם *benoteihem* and חתנות *chatnut* and
intermarriage and so on, right? Sounds like that sort of... which is
what, you know, whenever you read all this stuff about wine and
how they're afraid of intermarriage, you say, 'What? Wine's the problem, but
going out for drinks is okay?' You know, so that's exactly what
this beer seems like an extension of. Okay. אמר רב *Amar Rav*:
האי שיכרא דארמאה *hai shichra de-arma'ah*—this beer of the non-Jews—שרי *shari* is
permissible. וחייא ברי Vichiya bri, לא נשתי מיניה lo nishti minei, *ve-Chiya
b'ri lo nishti mineih*. But Chiya my son shouldn't drink from it.
So גמרא *Gemara* says, ממה נפשך *mima nafshach*, make up your mind.
אי שרי לכולי עלמא שרי *ei shari lekulei alma shari*. If it's
okay, to everybody it should be okay, even for your son. אי
אסור לכולי עלמא אסור *ei assur lekulei alma assur*. If it's a
problem, it should be forbidden for everyone. אלא רב סבר משום גילויא
*Ela Rav savar mishum gilluya*. רב *Rav* thinks the problem is that
it's exposed. ואזיל מרורא דכשותא וקלי ליה *ve-azil merora de-kashuta ve-kali leh*.
But the bitterness of the כשותא *kashuta*—what's כשותא *kashuta* there? Hops? Did
they say what? I forgot to look. Hops, right. So it is
beer. The bitterness of the hops comes and destroys the poison. So
even if some some snake drinks from it, it's neutralized by the
hops.
וקלי ליה זיחריה destroys the poison. ודלקי, Vedalaki, but somebody who's already
sick, מלקי טפי, malki tfei, it does injure their health. וחייא ברי,
Chiya my son, הוא דלקי, hu dalaki, since he's not of good
strong constitution, לא נשתי מיניה, he shouldn't drink from it. Okay. אמר,
last point and where we keep on going back and forth from
this exposed stuff exposed, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, כל השרצים יש להם
ארס, kol hashratzim yesh lahem eres, all various types of whatever rodents
or not rodents, whatever, anyway, creepy-crawlies, creeping animals have poison. של נחש
ממית, Shel nachash memis, but that of the snake is fatal. של
שרצים אינו ממית, Shel shratzim eino memis, others not. I guess he
never dealt with a
scorpion. Okay. What?
There's no way. There were scorpions.
I know, I was teasing.
No, I know, but you
know, I mean is the
scorpion included in the שרצים? shratzim?
Maybe not, I don't know. Okay. אמר ליה שמואל, Amar leh Shmuel,
so Shmuel said to לחייא בר רב, leChiya bar Rav, בר אריא,
Bar arya, son of lions, תא ואימא לך מלתא מעלייתא דאמר רב
אבוך, ta ve'eima lach milta ma'alyata de'amar Rav avuch, let me tell
you some great thing that רב your father said. הכי אמר אבוך,
Hachi amar avuch, here's what your father said. הני ארמאי זוקני, Hanei
armaei zukani, these non-Jews that are like that are a little bloated,
maybe he means fat. דהוו שתו גלוייא ולא
מיתו, Dehavu shatu gilluya velo meisu, why is it that they drink
like if we as Jews are so careful about exposed liquids, how
come we look all around us and the non-Jews drink it and
they don't die? איידי דאכלי שקצים ורמשים חביל גופייהו, Aidi de'achli shkutzim
u'remashim chavil gufeihu, since they anyway eat these creepy-crawlies, so therefore they've
already developed a tolerance for the poison and that's why they don't
die. Okay, so we'll end with this, but obviously very important two
things: one about the different types of seals, a long תוספות trying
to discuss what how exactly we פסקן about that, transporting and shipping
wine. Oh, I never got back to say, because actually the גמרא
didn't say, I said the גמרא was going to but it was
actually רש"י, what the middle position is and it's still never really
explained. Like if you're afraid about tampering, say it should be like
totally forbidden, and it winds up being like some middle level, like
we're afraid it would be tampered with but we don't totally assume
it, so like some middle idea that you can't drink it but
you can get benefit, right? So there are all those three possibilities
with if, you know, A, are we not afraid it's tampered at
all, B, we're so afraid it's even forbidden in benefit, C, some
unclear middle position that don't drink it but you can get benefit.
Okay, but then of course this really interesting thing about the prohibition
of beer which was really, like I said, chipped away at and
I don't know anybody who really practices this prohibition, you know, but
and the גמרא itself sort of came out of thin air. Okay,
we will stop here.